Register of the C. Frank Glass papers
Hoover Institution Archives
C. Frank Glass papers
1913-1987
2004C12
Glass, C. Frank (Cecil Frank), 1901-1988
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, police reports, personal documents, printed matter, photographs, and postcards, relating to Trotskyism in South Africa, China and the United States. Includes many letters by Rayna Prohme, American revolutionary journalist in China and sister-in-law of Glass.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2004.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1901 Born, Birmingham, England
1909 Immigrated to South Africa
1921 Founding member, Communist Party of South Africa
1931 Relocated to China
1932-1933 Tass News Agency writer, Shanghai
1934-1935 Shanghai Evening Post and Mercury reporter
1935-1936 Shanghai Times reporter
1935-1937 Secretary, Communist League of China
1938-1941 China Weekly Review writer, Shanghai
1942 Relocated to the United States
1944-1963 National Committee member, Socialist Workers Party
1988 Died, Los Angeles, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Cecil Frank Glass was a radical journalist and revolutionary political activist on three continents. He was a founding member of the Communist Party of South Africa in 1921, and in 1928 became an early adherent of the International Left Opposition led by Leon Trotsky. After relocating to Shanghai, China, in 1931, he spent most of the next decade there, working as a journalist. Concurrently he was actively involved in rebuilding the Trotskyist movement in China, and was a member of the Central Committee of the Communist League of China. Glass was closely associated with radical American journalists in Shanghai, including Wilbur Burton and Harold Isaacs. There he also met the American Grace Simons (1901-1985). She was first married to Burton and afterwards to Glass. Grace's older sister Rayna Simons Prohme (1894-1927) had been a prominent figure among Western revolutionaries involved with the Left Guomindang, had edited the Peking People's Tribune and other journals, and had been an associate of Mikhail Borodin and Song Qingling (Madame Sun Yat-sen). Rayna accompanied Madame Sun to the Soviet Union following the failure of the 1927 revolution in China, and died suddenly in Moscow, evidently of a brain tumor.
After two trips to the United States and Mexico (where he conferred with Trotsky) during the 1930s, Glass relocated permanently to the United States during World War II. There, he was for years a leading member of the Socialist Workers Party, but eventually developed a more sympathetic view of the Maoist government of China than could easily be reconciled with an orthodox Trotskyist position.
In political work Glass made use of the pseudonyms Frank Graves, Li Fu-ren and John Liang. He is the subject of a biography by Baruch Hirson, The Restless Revolutionary: Frank Glass (London: Porcupine Press, 2003).
The C. Frank Glass papers in the Hoover Institution Archives were acquired from Susan Weissman in 2003. The collection is small. There are also Glass papers at Concordia College in Toronto, Ontario, but it seems likely that many other papers did not survive.
The collection is arranged in four series: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, and Audiovisual File. Of particular interest are many lengthy letters by Rayna Prohme, some written to her sister Grace, and some written to her second husband William Prohme and passed on to Grace when Prohme died in 1935. The collection also includes printed copies of political articles by Glass, and photocopies of surveillance reports on Glass and associates made by British, French and American police and consular authorities in Shanghai.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Fourth International.; Communism--South Africa.; Communism--China.; Communism--United States.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Americans--China.; Prohme, Rayna Simons, 1894-1927.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1921-1987 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically. Third-party letters are entered under name of writer.
  - Chang, Ke, 1987 (Folder 1: 1)
  - De Wet, Madge (sister of Frank Glass), 1954-1987 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Glass, Grace Simons (wife of Frank Glass), 1942 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Grunfeld, A. Tom, 1984-1986 (Folder 1: 4)
  - International Secretariat for the Fourth International, 1934-1936 (Folder 1: 5)
    Compilation of transcriptions of letters and excerpts from letters by Glass and others
  - Isaacs, Harold R., 1985 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Library of Social History, undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Powell, John B., 1944 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Prohme, Rayna (Folder 1)
    Letters from Rayna Prohme to her sister Grace Simons and to her first and second husbands, Samson Raphaelson and William Prohme.
    - 1921-1925 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1927 (en route to and in Moscow) (Folder 1: 10)
  - Prohme, William (second husband of Rayna Prohme), 1927-1935 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
    Letters from Prohme to Grace Simons and her first husband Wilbur Burton, and to Helen Freeland and Vincent Sheean
  - Shanghai Times, 1936 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Sheean, Vincent, 1927 (Folder 1: 13)
    Letters from Sheean in Moscow to Helen Freeland and Samson Raphaelson re the death of Rayna Prohme
  - Sinclair, Louis, 1985-1987 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Strong, Anna Louise, 1927 (Folder 1: 15)
    Letters from Strong in Moscow to Samson Raphaelson and to the mother of Rayna Prohme re her death
  - Tass News Agency, 1932 (Folder 1: 16)
  - United States. War Department, 1944 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Wang, Fanxi, 1985-1987 (Folder 1: 18)
- Speeches and writings, 1932-1962 (Box 1)
  Speeches and writings by C. Frank Glass, arranged chronologically
  - "What I Saw in the Shanghai War," Johannesburg Sunday Times, 1932 May 22 (Folder 1: 19)
    Written under the pseudonym A South African. Printed copy.
  - "The War Lords Go 'Left,'" New Masses, 1934 January 16 (Folder 1: 20)
    Printed copy
  - "The End of the Chinese Soviets," New International, 1938 January (Folder 1: 21)
    Written under the pseudonym Li Fu-ren. Printed copy
  - "After the Fall of Wuhan," New International, 1939 January (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Lessons and Perspectives of the Sino-Japanese War," Fourth International, 1941 February (Folder 1: 23)
    Written under the psuedonym Li Fu-ren. Printed copy
  - "Chen Tu-hsiu: Chinese Revolutionist," Fourth International, 1942 August (Folder 1: 24)
  - "Japan Faces the Abyss," Fourth International, 1944 February-April (Folder 1: 25)
    Three-part series written under the pseudonym Li Fu-ren. Printed copy
  - "Leon Trotsky, Revolutionary Teacher of the Colonial Peoples," Fourth International, 1944 August (Folder 1: 26)
  - "Imperialist Program for the Orient," Fourth International, 1945 June (Folder 1: 27)
  - "War Guilt in the Pacific: A Political Analysis of the Pearl Harbor Reports," Fourth International, 1945 October (Folder 1: 28)
  - "China After World War II," Fourth International, 1946 July (Folder 1: 29)
  - Vigilante Terror in Fontana: The Tragic Story of O'Day H. Short and His Family, 1946 (Folder 1: 30)
    Pamphlet re black victims of racial attack in Fontana, California, published under the authorship of Myra Tanner Weiss, but ghostwritten for her by Glass. Printed copy
  - "The Kuomintang Faces Its Doom: Civil War in China," Fourth International, 1949 February (Folder 1: 31)
  - "China: A World Power," Fourth International, 1951 January-February (Folder 1: 32)
  - Our China Policy: An Open Letter to All the Members of the Socialist Workers Party, 1962 October 14 (Folder 1: 33)
    Written under the psudonym John Liang. Typescript
  - Sykee, the Wonk, undated (Folder 1: 34)
    Typescript
- Subject File, 1913-1985 (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by topic
  - China (Folder 2)
    - Shanghai French Concession police reports (photocopies) on Glass, Grace Simons Burton (later Glass), Alexander Buchman and others, 1935-1938 (Folder 2: 1)
      Includes English translations
    - Shanghai Municipal Police Special Branch reports (photocopies) on Glass, Wilbur Burton, Harold Isaacs, William and Rayna Prohme, Richard Sorge and others, 1926-1933 (Folder 2: 2)
    - United States Department of State reports (photocopies) on Glass, Wilbur Burton and others, 1933-1937 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Clippings, 1927-1932 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Miscellany. Calling cards, letter of recommendation, notes, and Chinese document, 1926-1936 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Prohme, Rayna. Transcript of death certificate, "Rayna Simons Prohme: A Report on the Last Months of Her Life" by William Prohme (typescript), "Rayna: Letters from the Chinese Revolution" by Arthur J. Knodel (typescript), and clippings and other printed matter, 1913-1982 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Raphaelson, Samson (first husband of Rayna Prohme). Printed memoir by Raphaelson, 1981 (Folder 2: 7)
  - South Africa. Will of Gertrude Emily Glass (mother of Frank Glass), letters of recommendation, certificates and receipts, catalog of bookstore operated by Glass in Johannesburg, and printed matter, 1920-1930 (Folder 2: 8)
  - United States. Immigration visa documents, union membership cards, clippings re Simons family, and death certificate of Grace Simons Glass, 1929-1985 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Miscellany (Folder 2: 10)
- Audiovisual File, circa 1900s-1940s (Box 3: 10)
  Photographs and postcards
  - Photographs of individuals. Those depicted include Glass, Grace Simons Glass, Rayna Prohme, Tillman Durdin, Randall Gould and Harold Isaacs (Folder 3: 1)
  - Photographs of Simons family members (Folder 3: 2)
  - Photographs of Wilbur Burton (first husband of Grace Simons) (Folder 3: 3)
  - Postcards of scenes in South Africa (Folder 3: 4)
  - Photographs of scenes in China (Folder 3: 5)
  - Negatives (Folder 3: 6)
  - Photocopies of printed reproductions of photographs. Those depicted include Glass, Grace Simons Glass, Rayna Prohme, Wilbur Burton and John Reed (Folder 3: 7)
  - Glass plate of scene in China (Folder 3: 8)